<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at Colchester, June 2. 1697. Before the Right Honourable and Reverend Father in God Henry Lord Bishop of London, at a conference with his clergy upon His Majesty's late injunctions. / By H. De Luzancy ... ; Printed by his Lordship's special command. ; To which are prefixed some remarks on the Socinians late answer to the four letters written against them by the same author.</title>
            <author>De Luzancy, H. C. (Hippolyte du Chastelet), d. 1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21416</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 9527755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2423A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 226.f.17[10]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26743</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99889438</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99889438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">193432</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21416)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 193432)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; B7:3[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at Colchester, June 2. 1697. Before the Right Honourable and Reverend Father in God Henry Lord Bishop of London, at a conference with his clergy upon His Majesty's late injunctions. / By H. De Luzancy ... ; Printed by his Lordship's special command. ; To which are prefixed some remarks on the Socinians late answer to the four letters written against them by the same author.</title>
                  <author>De Luzancy, H. C. (Hippolyte du Chastelet), d. 1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Holt for Tho. Bennet, at the Half Moon in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 2nd, I, 13 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Socinianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:193432:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:193432:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D AT <hi>COLCHESTER, June</hi> 2. 1697. BEFORE THE Right Honourable and Reverend Father in GOD, HENRY Lord Biſhop of <hi>LONDON,</hi> AT A Conference with his CLERGY UPON <hi>His MAJESTY'S late Injunctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> H. De LUZANCY, B. D. <hi>Vicar of</hi> 
               <choice>
                  <abbr>DOVERC.</abbr>
                  <expan>DOVERCOURT</expan>
               </choice> 
               <hi>and</hi> HARWICH.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="blackletterType">Printed by his Lordſhip's Special Command.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To which are prefixed ſome Remarks on the <hi>Socinians</hi> late Anſwer to the <hi>Four Letters</hi> written againſt them by the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Holt</hi> for <hi>Tho. Bennet,</hi> at the <hi>Half Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:193432:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:193432:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">To the Reverend Clergy at the Conference,</hi> 
               <date>June 2.</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe, when pronounc'd before our <hi>moſt Excellent Dioceſan,</hi> had the Happineſs to meet with ſo great an Approbation from you, that even in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect you might have challeng'd its firſt appearing in the World: But by your unanimous Application to <hi rend="blackletterType">His Lordſhip,</hi> that he would be pleas'd to command me to make it publick, it became entirely your own; and I could not without Injuſtice look for any other, or ſafer Patronage, than that of ſo many wiſe and learned Men, who did me the Honour to deſire its Publication.</p>
            <p>But there is alſo a great mixture of <hi>Gratitude</hi> in the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer which I humbly make to you of it. I am glad of ſo publick an Opportunity to expreſs to you the deep Sence which I have of your repeated Favours to my Pariſh, which for four Years laſt paſt you have honour'd with a Lecture, wherein you propos'd to your ſelves no other Encouragement but that of doing Good; your pious Endeavours being like Vertue, which is a Reward to it ſelf, and is abundantly ſatisfy'd if it can but advance the Great Ends of Religion I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Reverend Brethren,</hi>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Humble, and Obedient Servant,</hi> LUZANCY,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:193432:3"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>HIs Majeſty's late Injunctions are the Subject of the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: How wiſe they are in themſelves, and how ſuitable to the Exigencies of the Church, is viſible to any one, who is never ſo little acquainted with the Diſputes of the preſent Age. The <hi>Socinians</hi> by oppoſing the Belief of the Holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> and the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Jeſus Chriſt, having brought Religion into Danger, there appear'd Writers of all ſorts to defend the Grand and Common Concern of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. But they being Men of different Education, Studies, and Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, manag'd the Sacred Controverſie in a different way from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Some excellently vers'd in Eccleſiaſtical Learning, and great Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as well as Judges of <hi>Tradition,</hi> ſtuck firmly to the Deciſions of the Sacred Councils, and the Determinations of the Fathers: Some addicted to the Speculations of the Schools, follow'd a more abſtruſe and metaphyſical Method: Others us'd to a Philoſophical way of arguing, would bring our Myſteries within the uſual and receiv'd Principles of reaſoning. But all this was not done with the ſame Abilities and Succeſs. Some made the Judgment of the Catholick Church before, and after the great Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> to appear with a vaſt Clearneſs and Evidence: Some did ſhew to the learned World, how Grapes may be gather'd of Thorns; and the manner of ſpeaking of the Schools become not only plain, but alſo florid, and eloquent: Others thought that God had stamp'd in us the Image of his incomprehenſible Operations: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy in this, that they gave to weak Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes the Name of Demonſtrations, and justly anger'd the preſent, by ridiculing the Terms us'd by the Ancient Church.</p>
            <p>This, though indeed well deſign'd of all hands, yet met not with all the Succeſs which might have been hop'd for. It inflam'd the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and made them not ſo much to weigh the Truth it ſelf, as to ſtrive to find ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in every one of theſe ways. The firſt being moſt Matter of Fact, was very hard to be oppos'd; and whoſoever reads ſeriouſly the Anſwer to the learned Doctor <hi>Bull,</hi> and is in any degree acquainted with Antiquity, muſt needs wiſh for more Exactneſs and Candor in the Author of that Writing. The ſecond they have profeſſedly miſunderſtood, owning Dr. <hi>South</hi> as exact and as cloſe a Writer as ever was, to ſpeak the Sence of the Church, but willing to miſtake that Sence, and confounding it with <hi>Sabellianiſm,</hi> which the Church ever did, and does now deteſt. The third having given them great Advantages, they have crowded one Print upon the neck of another, and the Authority of the Divine Oracles laid aſide, Philoſophy becomes the Judge of Religion; and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> or <hi>Des Cartes</hi> impeach Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>But this is not all: Several learned Men amongſt us could not bear with
<pb facs="tcp:193432:3"/> theſe new Notions, or think their Silence juſtifiable to God and his Church in this Matter: They exprest themſelves warmly againſt thoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncatholick Terms and Explications, but were anſwer'd again with Heat and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; and a War began of a ſtrange and unaccountable Nature; all Parties agreeing in the ſame Deſign to maintain our Holy Myſteries, and yet divided in the way of purſuing it.</p>
            <p>The Injunctions obviated all this, by giving a check to a ſwarm of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> Prints, which with great Industry were diſperſt over the Kingdom; and obliging Divines not only to treat theſe Sacred Matters calmly, but alſo to uſe no other Expreſſions in their Explications, but what the Churches of God have us'd themſelves to: A wiſe and a truly Chriſtian Expedient to preſerve the Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church! For of all the Societies which make up the Catholick Church, none ever pretended to ſay any new thing in this Matter; but as they receiv'd the Faith, ſo they deliver'd it to us: And to any rational Man, it is a mighty Argument againſt <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> that thoſe very Churches which have, and do differ amongſt themſelves in ſo many other Points, never differ'd in this; and that the great Variety of Superſtructures never in the leaſt affected the Foundation.</p>
            <p>I hope that this has in a very great meaſure laid the Heats rais'd amongſt us: But it has not ſilenc'd the <hi>Socinians;</hi> thô indeed it appears to me by their lateſt Prints ſince the publiſhing of the Injunctions, that they write more out of a deſire to have it ſaid, that they have left no Book un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwer'd, than really to ſatisfie themſelves and others concerning thoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Arguments, which have been offer'd to them. This is the moſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Conſtruction which I can make of the Anſwers to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> the Lords Biſhops of <hi>Sarum</hi> and <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and the incomparable Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> But I think the Anſwer to my Book to be a ſingular Inſtance of this. A Friend of mine, who is a Gentleman of that Perſwaſion, had often told me that there was one coming, and I expected it with ſome Impatience, deſirous to ſee what they had to ſay to ſome plain Arguments, which I thought of great force, and how they would vindicate ſo many Places out of their own Books, which they own'd I had cited with a great deal of Truth and Juſtice. At laſt my Friend ſhews me their lateſt Collection of Anſwers, amongſt which there is one <hi>to the four Letters of M. H. de L.</hi> I hope it will not be taken amiſs if I make ſome Remarks upon it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is very diverting to ſee a Writing call'd an Anſwer to the four Letters; and not ſo much as a Page, or Line, or Tittle of the four Letters touch'd. I confeſs that this is an eaſie way of anſwering, and that at this rate any Book upon Earth may be anſwer'd. Any Body may have the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be an Author. But I am not altogether ſatisfied, that this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with that reputation of Learning and Eloquence which theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:193432:4"/> men have ſo juſtly acquir'd. One or two more ſuch Anſwers, will, I am afraid, ſink, or at leaſt endanger a part of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They give a rare reaſon for not meddling with the four Letters. <hi>I know not,</hi> ſays the Author, <hi>p.</hi> 47. <hi>whether we are concern'd in them, till I know more certainly in what Sence he holds a Trinity of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons, and the Divinity and Satisfaction of our Saviour?</hi> I beg leave of theſe Gentlemen to aſſert, that they know as well as I do my ſelf, what is my ſence in thoſe Matters. Obſcurity is none of the many defects which the four Letters may be charg'd with: But they were not willing to intangle themſelves in the diſcuſſion of ſo many Citations, or to make good the weak ſide of their Writings, which they were ſenſible could not be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd. They have found of late a ſhorter Cut; and that is, the famous diſtinction <hi>of Real and Nominal Trinitarians:</hi> They ſteal away with this on all occaſions, and ſtill maintain a running Fight: It is their laſt refuge; and had it not been for the rare contrivance, there had been before this an end of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Controverſie. To anſwer a ſolid Argument, is a hard, and generally an unfortunate Task: But if they can but bring you right or wrong within the Verge of the fatal Diſtinction, then they have always a large Field for Diſcourſe: They act in this like ingenious, but whether altogether like conſcientious Men, I am not willing to determine?</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are ſo full of that beloved diſtinction, and ſo fond of meeting with any thing that looks like it, that in what they call an Anſwer to the <hi>Four Letters,</hi> they have done to themſelves and to me a real Injury. To themſelves by a flat contradiction in the ſpace of four Pages; and to me, by charging me with that which I never ſaid or thought: They make me ſay that the Divine Perſons are Three Infinite Spirits. Pag. 43. <hi>He ſays Three Infinite Spirits each of them a God, are all of them but One God:</hi> I averr that there is nothing in the <hi>Four Letters</hi> which directly, or indirectly looks like that: It is not the Language of Scripture, nor that of the Catholick Church: It never was, and I hope ſhall never be mine. But this they have contradicted, <hi>Pag.</hi> 47. by deſiring to know, <hi>in what Sence I hold a Trinity of Divine Perſons.</hi> One would be apt to ſay that this betrays a great deal of Incogitancy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Four Letters</hi> then are ſtill ſound and ſafe; but the Preface is engag'd, and I muſt endeavour to bring it off. Two things in it are excepted againſt: The one, that I ſaid, <hi>That the Conſent of the whole Chriſtian World muſt be a ſtrong Inducement to a modeſt <hi>Socinian</hi> to miſtruſt all his Arguments, and that to oppoſe all that is great and good in the Church of God in a Point of Faith,</hi> which Word the Author of the Anſwer has overlook'd, <hi>is too much for the moſt preſuming Diſputant.</hi> He ſays to this, <hi>p.</hi> 40. <hi>that the caſe is this; one ſide has Argument, the other has Authority and Number: And that in a Claſh between Argument
<pb facs="tcp:193432:4"/> and Number, that whole World, and all that is great in it, when weigh'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt but one Argument, is as if you had put nothing at all into the Scale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay that he abſolutely miſtakes the Caſe. We maintain that the Church has Reaſon, as well as Authority and Number; and that on this very Account a modeſt <hi>Socinian</hi> muſt loſe much of his Confidence. By all that is great and good, I mean the Sacred Councils, the Holy and Learned Fathers, and the different Societies of Chriſtians all the World over, who have been baptiz'd in the Name of that Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity, and look upon <hi rend="blackletterType">Ieſus Chriſt</hi> as the Author and Finiſher of their Faith. In a Point of Faith, and much leſs in the Foundation, God will not ſuffer the Catholick Church to err. Had I ſaid that it had been a <hi>Reaſon</hi> to a modeſt <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> to miſtruſt all his Arguments, I had ſaid nothing but what is exactly true: I confeſs I was too modeſt my ſelf in calling it only an <hi>Inducement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The other Exception is againſt an Aſſertion, which I thought no Divine in the World would have diſputed; That Faith and Reaſon are two different things; and, conſequently, that that which is the Object of Faith, cannot be the Object of Reaſon. He calls this, <hi>p.</hi> 41. <hi>a very raſh Propoſition.</hi> He ſays ſome lines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>That the Apoſtle teaches, <hi>Heb. 11.1.</hi> not only that the Object of Faith and Reaſon is the ſame; but that there cannot be Faith without Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and that Faith is the Product of Reaſon.</hi> This Author ſhould have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, before he call'd <hi>the Propoſition raſh,</hi> that it is the Sence of all the Ancient and Modern Divines; and that thô ſometimes Faith and Reaſon are converſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame Object; as for inſtance, in the Exiſtence and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God, which Reaſon conſiders as well as Faith; yet for all that, their Object is different, and even in this very caſe, Reaſon aſſents to it, as it is naturally known; and Faith, as it is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturally reveal'd. The place of the Apoſtle ſhould not have been mention'd at all. For what is the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> but a Revelation of thoſe things which Reaſon cannot reach, or penetrate; and on this very account are ſaid to be <hi>unſeen,</hi> and is that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration,</hi> which riſing from an higher Principle, is different from, and has a greater Certainty than Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But what this Author ſays, That <hi>there can be no Faith without Reaſon, and that Faith is the Product of Reaſon,</hi> ſhews plainly the misfortune of writing An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers in haſte. If by the firſt of theſe Propoſitions he means that Faith is always rational, and that Reaſon never wants ſtrong Inducements to believe, which the Schools in their rugged Language call <hi>Motives of Credibility,</hi> I ſay ſo too. But if he means, that we cannot believe, except we have a clear Notion of what is propos'd to our Belief; I ſay, that it is againſt the Nature of Faith, which offers things above Reaſon, and expects the ſubmiſſion of our Judgments to the Authority of the Revelation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Propoſition that Faith is the Product of Reaſon, is capable of a tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sence, if by it is meant no more, than that Reaſon is an introduct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on to Faith: But if by it is meant, that it is the Cauſe of Faith, I muſt beg this Author's leave to ſay, that it is plain <hi>Pelagianiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:193432:5"/>
            <p n="6">6. This Gentleman asks me ſeveral Queſtions, wherein I muſt take the liberty to tell him that I am not at all concern'd, and conſequently not oblig'd to anſwer. He argues very ſmartly againſt Three Infinite Minds, Spirits, or Subſtances; thô, at the ſame time, I doubt he makes his Adverſaries to ſay more than really they do. I leave him and them to diſpute it; yet one of them I think is a Queſtion by no means to be offer'd, and takes off much of the reſpect due to the Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>This therefore,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is the firſt Queſtion that I deſire Mr. <hi>L.</hi> to reſolve: Will he believe a Doctrine that ſeems to imply manifeſt and inconteſtable Contradictions, if ſuch Doctrine or Propoſition were indeed found in Scripture?</hi> To this, I anſwer, that the Queſtion is unreaſonable, becauſe the Suppoſition on which it is grounded is impoſſible. God cannot contradict himſelf. A manifeſt and unconteſtable Contradiction in Scripture, is a thing not ſo much as to be thought of from him, who is Light, and in whom there is no Darkneſs at all. But I well go farther with this Gentleman; and thô I love and honour Reaſon as much as any Man in the World, yet I will affirm, that if it were poſſible that in any undoubted Scripture there ſhould be in clear and expreſs Terms a Propoſition or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which ſeems to imply a manifeſt and inconteſtable Contradiction, I ought not to reject it, or make my Reaſon the Judge of God's Veracity: But my Duty is humbly to reſign my ſelf to him, and adore what I cannot underſtand.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I know that this Gentleman will take this very ill; and will ſay again, as he has already, <hi>p.</hi> 41. that <hi>I calumniate Reaſon, the Light ſet up in us by God himſelf.</hi> But that Light is not given us to impeach and reproach our Maker; and reject what he commands us to believe, or call it <hi>a manifeſt and inconteſtable Contradiction,</hi> becauſe it is above its weak Perceptions: That Light ought to act in its due meaſure and proportion; if it goes farther, it is a Rebellion and an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt the Majeſty and Power of God. He calumniates Reaſon, who does detract from its Dignity and Energy in thoſe things wherein it ought to be Judge. It is an Affront to Reaſon to be brought below it ſelf: But he alſo calumniates Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who exalts it more than it deſerves; as he no leſs maliciouſly injures a Man, who commends in him Qualities which he has not, than he who obſcures and denies thoſe which he has. There are ſome General Principles wherein Reaſon cannot err, and which Man ought to be guided by. None is more plain and evident than this, that he owes his ſubmiſſion and aſſent to what God propoſes: Whether it be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, or not comprehenſible, is no part of the Inquiry? Whether God has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd it, is the true ſtate of the Queſtion? Reaſon has a Right to examine, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God has propos'd it, or no? The danger of taking things upon Truſt, is too great to deny Reaſon the power of examining. But that Point once clear'd, to ſay that we ought not to ſubmit, becauſe it is incomprehenſible, or appears to us manifeſtly contradictory, is an ill and an endleſs way of arguing.</p>
            <p n="8">8. This Author cannot digeſt the Epithets of <hi>Narrow</hi> and <hi>Corrupt,</hi> which I gave to Reaſon. He complains of it in ſeveral places of his ſmall Writing. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is not our Reaſon ſuch? Can he who denies this, pretend that he ever endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
<pb facs="tcp:193432:5"/> to know himſelf? I have often wonder'd at the pains which ſome Men have taken to convince the Oppoſers of the Doctrine of Original Sin. The ſhorteſt and eaſieſt Method was to ſend them to themſelves, to find there the fatal conſequences of the firſt Tranſgreſſion. I appeal to my ingenious Adverſary, who thô certainly a great Maſter of Reaſon, yet upon ſecond Thoughts will agree with me that the Reaſon of the beſt Men is very Narrow and Corrupt. Whence do proceed ſo many Miſtakes and Errors, Miſapprehenſions and Inadvertencies, but from that very Principle? Is not this the Spring of ſo many hot and tedious Diſputes? And what Reaſon but this can be given of ſo many Books and Opinions which have divided Mankind?</p>
            <p>In this the Excellency of Faith appears, and for this we ought to praiſe its Author, the <hi rend="blackletterType">Holy Ieſus,</hi> that it has rectify'd and improv'd Reaſon not only by making it more knowing, but alſo more humble, more ſincere, and more obedient to God.</p>
            <p>I am ſure that this is the Method of arguing of the Primitive Fathers in that mighty ſtruggle with the Heathen Philoſophers, ſome of whom did ſo exalt Reaſon as to pretend to decide of every thing; whilſt others did ſo revile it, as to be poſitive that nothing could certainly be known; and conſecrated that wild and extravagant Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Socrates, Hoc unum ſcio nihil ſcio.</hi> This I know that I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Both diſputed admirably one againſt another. But when the Apologiſts for Chriſtianity were oblig'd to take in hand the Cauſe of Religion; althô they had the true Notion of Reaſon, <hi>Res Dei Ratio,</hi> ſays elegantly <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and knew it to be the Light of God in us, yet they own'd it to be <hi>narrow</hi> and <hi>corrupted,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently not Reaſon, but Faith and Revelation to be attended to. Thus <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Arnobius, Tertullian, Lactantius,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and others: <hi>Tertullian</hi> de Anima, c. 1. <hi>Cui enim veritas comperta ſine Deo? Cui Deus cognitus ſine Chriſto? Cui Chriſtus exploratus ſine Spiritu Sancto? Cui Spiritus Sanctus accommodatus ſine Fidei Sacramento:</hi> And St. <hi>Auſtin de morib. Eccl. Cath. c.</hi> 2. A Book never enough to be read; who ſpeaks of Reaſon in Terms which muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly pleaſe thoſe Gentlemen, calling it, <hi>Perſpicuitas, &amp; ſanctitas Rationis,</hi> the <hi>Clearneſs and Sanctity of Reaſon;</hi> yet ſays, that it is ſo much obſcur'd by Sin, Paſſion, and Prejudice, that, <hi>Saluberrime comparatum eſt, ut in lucem Verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aciem titubantem, &amp; velut ramis humanitatis opacatam inducat authoritas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. This ſhews how much this Gentleman is in the wrong, when he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 42. that <hi>I muſt be content to argue theſe Queſtions about the Trinity and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation not from Scripture only, but from Reaſon alſo; nay, from <hi rend="blackletterType">Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon chiefly and ultimately.</hi>
               </hi> As far as Reaſon is ſubſervient to find the Truth and Certainty of the Revelation, I confeſs that I muſt argue from Reaſon; and the <hi>Chiefly and ultimately</hi> is capable of a good Sence; becauſe the belief of our Myſteries is at laſt reſolv'd into this moſt rational Propoſition, That I muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what God has reveal'd; and that to find that it is ſo in the ſacred and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Scriptures, is certainly the Work of Reaſon. But if he means that, the Authority of God's Word laid aſide, we muſt bring thoſe Myſteries to the Scrutiny of Reaſon; and inſtead of Divine, uſe only Humane and Philoſophical Diſcepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:193432:6"/> I ſay that it is a new, an unreaſonable, and an unchriſtian Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>It is new: For this very Author is too much converſant with Antiquity, not to know, that in the long Conteſts between the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and the <hi>Arrians, Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> &amp;c. the Scripture was appeal'd to on both ſides: They never thought of pretended Impoſſibilities, <hi>manifeſt and inconteſtible Contradictions.</hi> The Certainty of the Revelation, was the only proof aim'd at; That the Scripture plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught it, was affirm'd by the Church; That it was not, was maintain'd by Hereticks. Indeed Tradition had a ſhare in the Diſpute: For no Scripture being of private Interpretation, the Sence of the Primitive Doctors was strictly inquir'd after; but all ſtill was reſolv'd into the Teſtimony of God in the Sacred Writings. Yet theſe Times had their Orators, their Philoſophers, their Criticks; and it is ſtrange, that none of them could perceive, that one, and one, and one, are not one but three; and that <hi>this manifeſt and inconteſtable Contradiction</hi> ſhould only be a diſcovery of the <hi>Socinians</hi> in this Age.</p>
            <p>It is alſo unjuſt and unreaſonable: For the manner of treating a Diſpute, muſt have ſome proportion with the thing in Diſpute. Phyſical Experiments are not ſearch'd into with Metaphyſical Speculations; nor metaphyſical Speculations clear'd by Phyſical Experiments. Criticiſms are unſerviceable in Geometry, and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Geometrician may be a lamentable Critick. Yet we have to deal with a ſort of Men, who will have Reaſon to decide of Matters above Reaſon; will make Faith and Reaſon, knowing and believing to be the ſame thing; and under pretence of Reaſoning, will rob God of his Power over us, and us of the Reward of our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to him.</p>
            <p>It is unchriſtian. If you deſign to diſpute with a Philoſopher, then go and ranſack <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> out with your Reaſon as ſplendidly, and profuſely as you can: But for me, who can ſay with <hi>Pacianus, Chriſtian is my Name, and Catholick is my Surname,</hi> I can, I will hear nothing but out of the Sacred Scriptures: Whatſoever you intend to teach me of God, muſt be fetch'd from thence. I never built the hopes of my Salvation upon <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> or <hi>Des Cartes:</hi> Their Writings are good in their kind; but to form Religion, they are thoſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns ſpoken of by the Prophet, <hi>broken Ciſterns that can hold no Water.</hi> In a Word, there we are to fix; and we cannot avoid diſputing eternally, if this is not made the Touch stone of all our Arguments. When we have indulg'd our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the utmoſt degree, it will prove an egregious Cheat to us, and we ſhall at laſt be oblig'd to return whence we came, and ſay as St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Epiſt. ad Voluſ. <hi>Dandum Deo aliquid poſſe, quod fateamur nos inveſtigare non poſſe. We muſt agree that God can do thoſe things,</hi> be capable of thoſe Operations and Communications, <hi>which we muſt be forc'd to acknowledge to be above all our Enquiries.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:193432:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 Tim. 1 13.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hold fast the Form of ſound Words.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALtho' the Church is a Divine Inſtitution, the Myſtical Body of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the Purchaſe of his Blood; Yet the Experience of all Ages has made it appear from the beginning of its happy Eſtabliſhment, that evil Men and Seducers have attempted not only to ruine its Out-works, but even to blow up its very Foundation. This <hi>Chriſt</hi> had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen when he told his Apoſtles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.7. that <hi>it muſt needs be that Offences come.</hi> This St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not unacquainted with, when he ſaid to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.19. <hi>There muſt be alſo Hereſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you:</hi> No Age or Society being without Men who love to abound in their own Sence; have not Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice enough to acknowledge their Weakneſs and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and will rather yield to Paſſion and Prejudice, than be led by the plain Aſſertions of Scripture, and the calm and ſerene Dictates of Reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:193432:7"/>
            <p>So great an Evil could not but vehemently affect that zealous Apoſtle, who had incumbent on him <hi>the Care of all the Churches.</hi> A truly Epiſcopal Spirit can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſit unconcern'd, and ſee them periſh for whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> dy'd. Nor could any way be found more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to prevent this, than that Men ſhould ſpeak the ſame things, and agree in uniform Expreſſions, as well as in the ſame Profeſſion of Faith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Now I beſeech you, Brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt that you all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no Schiſms among you; but that you be perfectly join'd together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ground of the excellent Direction given in the Text to <hi>Timothy, Hold faſt the Form of ſound Words.</hi> An Advice which, if neceſſary at any time, is certainly now of a vaſt Importance; when the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſt on one ſide, and the Diſputer of this World on the other, have rent Religion to pieces: When Men think it a Diſcredit to their Parts and Abilities, to <hi>think ſoberly:</hi> And inſtead of uniting againſt the Common Enemy, will rather ſuffer the War to be brought into their own Quarters, than part with their private, tho' crude and indigeſted Notions!</p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to theſe Words, I will endeavour to ſhew,
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>What is the Form of found Words?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>How dangerous it is to depart from it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>How we ought to behave our ſelves in relation to them who have departed from it?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Then, <hi>what is the Form of ſound Words?</hi> It is nothing elſe but a Collection of the ſeveral Verities dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd through the whole Body of the Sacred Scriptures.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:193432:7"/> An expreſs Form, as ſome have render'd it, not much different in this from the Sence of the <hi>Greek</hi> Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators: But more truly <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſhort Account, a Summary of Chriſtian Doctrine, by which Men come to know what to embrace, and what to refuſe. This St. <hi>Paul</hi> intends when he tells the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 6.17. <hi>that they have obey'd from the heart that Form of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which was deliver'd to them.</hi> But more agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the Original, <hi>into which they were deliver'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A noble Expreſſion, and elegantly treated by St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> in his Diſcourſe of Baptiſm. This the Apoſtle calls in the Verſe next to the Text, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that excellent Truſt committed to the Shepherds of the Flock, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. He will have no preaching, no eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of any Doctrine, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. All Sciences have their <hi>Axiomata,</hi> their firſt Principles, the ground of all their Demonſtrations. Chriſtianity has its <hi>Axiomata</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, on which all the reſt is built. Whatſoever we have to ſay, muſt be reduc'd to that, and without it ought not to be admitted.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Axiomata</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, theſe Fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtianity are, 1<hi>ſt.</hi> the <hi>Apoſtolical Creed.</hi> 2<hi>dly,</hi> Thoſe Enlargements on it, which the growth of Hereſies made neceſſary in the firſt General Councils. Theſe four which <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great profeſs'd to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence next to the four Goſpels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Creed, that <hi>unchangeable Rule of Faith,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls it. <hi>Cordis ſignaculum &amp; Fidei noſtrae Sacramentum.</hi> That which the Fathers underſtood by the <hi>anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God;</hi> that is, a ſolemn Profeſſion, Declaration of what Religion obliges us to believe, and from which we ought not to depart. This is the firſt Shield of Faith, which the Church oppos'd to the early Attempts of thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:193432:8"/> Hereticks who thought to have ſtifl'd her in her Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. This Confeſſion of <hi>God the Father, of his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son Jeſus Christ our Lord, and of the Holy Spirit,</hi> which is the Subſtance of that Creed, made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful the Endeavours of <hi>Simon, Cerinthus, Baſilides, Menander, Carpocrates,</hi> and the ſwarm of impure <hi>Gnoſticks.</hi> By this every Chriſtian was initiated to Religion, gave a reaſon of the Hope that was in him; and became a Member of that Society here on Earth, which after perſeverance in well doing is to be rewarded in Heaven.</p>
            <p>I know that a Critick of this Age, a Perſon of the firſt rank in the Common-wealth of Learning, has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted both the Antiquity and Univerſality of this Creed. A Notion too unadviſedly taken up by ſeveral Authors, who thought that the <hi>Socinians</hi> took too great an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from the Simplicity of its Articles. He made it to be only a Creed of the Latin or Weſtern Church, which the Catechumens were taught before their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Baptiſm. He produces two of St. <hi>Irenoeus,</hi> three of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> one of St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> three of <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> and inſiſts on ſome difference even between the Fathers who have been the Expoſitors of this Creed, St. <hi>Austin, Chryſologus, Maximus,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all this, whoſoever will look into the Creeds of St. <hi>Irenoeus,</hi> and <hi>Tertullian;</hi> for that of St. <hi>Cyril</hi> was after the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, and thoſe which <hi>Ruffinus</hi> has compar'd, that is, the <hi>Roman,</hi> the <hi>Aquileian,</hi> and the <hi>Oriental</hi> Creeds, will find ſo mighty an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the variations ſo minute and inconſiderable, as to make impoſſible any ſubſtantial difference.</p>
            <p>And it is certainly a ſtrange Fancy, that the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> ſhould take an advantage from the Simplicity of theſe Articles, which being but a Compendium of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:193432:8"/> New Teſtament, are at laſt reſolv'd into it. For the Sence of that Creed muſt be that of the Scriptures, of which it is an <hi>Epitome.</hi> And how can they argue againſt the Divinity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> from their not being call'd God in the Creed, when the Scriptures are ſo full in aſſerting the Unity of God, and the Trinity of Perſons in that one Adorable and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature? Are we not baptiz'd <hi>in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit? Are there not Three that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit,</hi> and <hi>are not theſe three one?</hi> Is not <hi>Christ</hi> declar'd to be, <hi>God bleſſed over all for ever?</hi> and <hi>God manifeſted in the Fleſh?</hi> Are we not told that <hi>the Spirit ſearches all things, even the deep things of God,</hi> and that <hi>to lye to the Holy Spirit, is to lye to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Objection is of that Clearneſs and Evidence, is ſo far from giving them any Advantage, and they have found themſelves ſo preſs'd by it, that they have been forc'd to ſplit on another Rock, and ſay that the Form of Baptiſm is no part of Scripture, and is only an addition to St <hi>Matthew.</hi> That the Place of St. <hi>John</hi> is another, and that the Word <hi rend="blackletterType">God,</hi> is not to be found in the cited Scriptures. Shifts unbecoming learned Men! Which even <hi>Praxeas</hi> and <hi>Sabellius</hi> would have bluſh'd at: The former oppos'd by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who tells him, <hi>that this Rule of Faith is come down to us from the beginning of the Goſpel.</hi> The latter by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who tells him, <hi>apud Euſeb.</hi> l. 7. c. 6. <hi>That the Perſons of the Father, Son, and Holy ſpirit are <hi rend="blackletterType">indiviſibly</hi> united in the ſame Divine Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2<hi>dly,</hi> The Forms agreed upon in the Primitive Councils, at <hi>Nice, Antioch, Sardis, Epheſus, Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Chalcedon,</hi> &amp;c. are no Additions to, but only Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the firſt Form. They are ſtill the Form of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:193432:9"/> ſound Words. It is not in the Power of the Church to make new Forms, new Articles of Faith: And in this the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is inexcuſable, and guilty of a Schiſm, which ſhe has charg'd others with. But to declare and explain the Faith, is an eſſential part of its Power. The growing Hereſies were the occaſion of the Apoſtolical Creed, the firſt Remedy apply'd to that raging Diſeaſe. The <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the vain and noiſie Oppoſitions of a pretended Knowledge, oblig'd them to deliver the ſacred Syſtem of Divine Verities. But when the old Hereticks were worn out, leaving to the World a ſad remembrance of their groſs Follies and Immoralities; and a new ſort ſprung up, who did attempt to overthrow the Faith once deliver'd to the Saints by Blaſphemous Heterodoxies. It was high time for the Church, to make the Creed more compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive than it was at firſt; give a greater extent to its Articles, and leave ſafe to future Ages the <hi>Depoſitum</hi> which they had receiv'd.</p>
            <p>And indeed it would have been very happy for the Church, if Men keeping to the Plainneſs and Simplicity of the Revelation, had not preſum'd to go farther. Oh, that an humble Faith had ſtifl'd Curioſity in its firſt At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to inquire into Divine Myſteries with weak Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocinations, and Philoſophy never aſſum'd to bring Divinity to be try'd at the Bar of humane Reaſon! Then <hi>Mercy and Truth would have kiſs'd each other, and God, even our God, would have given us his Bleſſing.</hi> But Man forgot that <hi>ſcrutator Majeſtatis opprimetur à Gloria,</hi> That the bold and daring Searcher into the Majeſty of God will be oppreſs'd and ſink under the weight of his Glory. He launch'd into a Sea in which the Rocks and Sands on all ſides threatn'd a ſad and inevitable Ruine.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:193432:9"/>
            <p>God has reveal'd to us his Exiſtence and the Unity of his Nature. He has told us, that in that one indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inſeparable Nature, are <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> He has aſſerted <hi>the Father to be God, the Son God, and the Holy Ghost God.</hi> He has taught us that <hi>the Father is not the Son, nor the Son the Father, nor the Holy Ghost Father or Son.</hi> He has inform'd us, that <hi>in the Fulneſs of times he ſent his only Son to take our Nature:</hi> That <hi>the Word was made Fleſh, and offer'd himſelf a Sacrifice for us.</hi> In ſuch plain Propoſitions as theſe has he commanded us to acquieſce. Faith is the Duty of this; Intuition and Knowledge the Privilege of another Life. The Perceptions of our preſent State, have no proportion with ſo incomprehenſible an Object. Had we ſtay'd there, the Church would have been <hi>a City at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity within it ſelf.</hi> But Man not contented with this, ſtrives to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that which God has not been pleas'd to reveal; that is, the <hi>Nexus,</hi> or manner of in being of the Three Perſons; The <hi rend="blackletterType">How,</hi> theſe three can be one; The Way of the Union of the two Natures in one adorable Perſon <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and having no other Guide but his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, intangles himſelf in inextricable Difficulties.</p>
            <p>Of this ſort were <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatum</hi> Patriarch of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, Photinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Syrmium, Praxeas, Noëtus, Sabellius, Arrius, Apollinaris, Neſtorius, Eutyches,</hi> and in this very Age <hi>Socinus</hi> the Reviver of the <hi>Samoſate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> and <hi>Photinian</hi> Hereſie. Theſe have been the Incendiaries of the Church, and the great Diſturbers of its Peace: The Men who have made it neceſſary to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the Form of ſound Words, and were the occaſion of the Creeds made in the Councils of which they bear the Names.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sabellius</hi> own'd the Unity of the Divine Nature;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:193432:10"/> but ſtruck with the Evidence of thoſe Texts which ſpeak the Son and the Holy Spirit to be <hi>God,</hi> could not deny a Trinity, but made it only to conſiſt of <hi>meer Names,</hi> or <hi>Denominations,</hi> as St. <hi>Baſil</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>Hom.</hi> 27. <hi>pag.</hi> 602. Or as St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> has it, <hi>one only Perſon, <hi rend="blackletterType">the Father</hi> acting under different Names.</hi> A Notion which the preſent <hi>Socinians</hi> ſeem too too willing to embrace. <hi>Arrius</hi> own'd a Trinity of Perſons, and not of Names. He ſaw that the poor ſhift of <hi>Sabellius</hi> was irreconcilable with that Oeconomy which ſo clearly appears in the Scriptures. But by admitting three Principles he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd the Unity of God, and was the firſt Author of the chymerical diſtinction of a God made and a God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made, of a Son <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the like, but not of the ſame Subſtance. <hi>Apollinaris</hi> own'd the Incarnation. <hi>The Word was made Fleſh,</hi> was an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of that Weight and Clearneſs, as gave not the leaſt ground to Primitive Ages for Allegories and little Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſms ſo much us'd in this. But he deſtroy'd the Union of the two Natures, by denying that Chriſt had a Soul, and leaving the Divinity to inform his Body. <hi>Neſtorius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> own'd the two Natures, but deny'd their Union in one Perſon. He would have two Perſons as well as two Natures. The <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the <hi>Man.</hi> The <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but not the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Eutyches</hi> acknowledged the Incarnation; but maintain'd a Singularity of Nature with that of a Perſon. He would have the Humanity to be abſorp'd, and the God to have annihilated the Man. All theſe the Church of God condemn'd by the Form of ſound Words contain'd in the ſeveral Creeds.</p>
            <p>The ſober Church of <hi>England</hi> ſenſible that even in point of Reformation we are apt to out-run the Mark; and under pretence of forſaking old Errors really fall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:193432:10"/> into new ones, has ſtrenuouſly aim'd at this, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede a Jot from the Form of ſound Words, and ſtick cloſe not only to the Sence, but even to the ways of ſpeaking of the Primitive Church. It has made the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical and Catholick Creeds a part of its Liturgy; and its very Articles concerning the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation,</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt are nothing elſe but a repetition of the Dogms of the Ancient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils.</p>
            <p>But before I conclude this Particular, I muſt ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that, which, tho' no part of the Form of ſound Words, has yet a very near relation to it; and that is, the Expreſſions us'd by the Fathers in their Debates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe Sacred Doctrines; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. and ſince adopted by all the Divines, and become the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Church. Concerning which I muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to aver, 1<hi>ſt.</hi> that whoſoever will be converſant in thoſe Diſputes, cannot without theſe Terms under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any part of them. 2<hi>dly,</hi> That they are proof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the Subterfuges and Equivocations of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. 3<hi>dly,</hi> That tho' it is much ſafer to keep to the Simplicity of the Form, and pretend to no Explication of that which we own to be incomprehenſible; yet if any can be pretended to, it is that, and that only which reſults from theſe Terms: But I ſhall no longer inſiſt on this, and come to the ſecond part of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>How dangerous it is to depart from the Form of ſound Words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am apt to think that it will give a great Light to what I have to ſay on this head, if I endeavour to ſhew before-hand which ways we depart from it. I conceive that it can be only theſe two. 1<hi>ſt. By re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the Article it ſelf, which is propos'd to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:193432:11"/> our Belief.</hi> 2<hi>dly, By admitting the Article, but uſing other Words than the Church to expreſs or explain it by.</hi> The one is abſolutely to depart from the ſound Words themſelves: The other, from the Form in which they are put.</p>
            <p>The firſt has been done by the Hereticks already mention'd. The unfortunate Attempt has been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd by <hi>Socinus,</hi> and his Followers; but by none ſo wholly, as by a ſort of pretended witty People, who aſham'd of the <hi>inhumane</hi> and irrational Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>unmanly Atheiſm,</hi> have under the Name of <hi rend="blackletterType">Deiſts</hi> endeavour'd to explode all reveal'd Religion. To theſe <hi>Socinus</hi> has lent moſt of their Arguments: From that ſide who have oppos'd a part of the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, theſe have learn'd to reject the whole. And tho' I ſhould think it unjuſt and uncharitable to think that the preſent <hi>Socinians</hi> are <hi>Deiſts,</hi> or give the <hi>Deiſts</hi> any deſign'd Encouragement; yet I will beg leave to aſſert, that taking an exact view of the <hi>Deiſtical</hi> and <hi>Socinian</hi> Syſtem, there will appear no very vaſt difference; <hi>Deiſm</hi> being nothing elſe but <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> improv'd; and <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> nothing elſe but <hi>Deiſm</hi> contracted.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, that is to keep to the Article, but put it in other Words, has been done by ſome amongſt our ſelves. Whether this has been the Effect of a too much indulg'd Curioſity, or of an imprudent Zeal: Whether the Heat of the Diſpute, and the preſſing Efforts of the Enemy has driven them from their Anchors? Whether they have been too fond of the Offspring of their own Brains; or whether a mixture of all theſe together has been the occaſion of it, is difficult to judge: But it is certain that the Preſs has groan'd under the burthen of new Diſcoveries; brought forth a ſwarm of Anſwers and Replies fuller of Heat than Light; and made it neceſſary for the Peace of the Church, that a Curtain
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:193432:11"/> ſhould be drawn over abundance of Writings, where Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Modeſty, and Candor ſhould have had a greater ſhare than really they can pretend to.</p>
            <p>Of the firſt of theſe, it is eaſie to ſhew, how dangerous it is to depart from the Form of ſound Words. For what greater danger can we fall into, than <hi>to make Shipwrack concerning the Faith?</hi> A State ſo much the more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, becauſe it deſtroys the very ground of our hopes. For <hi>he that believes ſhall be ſav'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He that does not believe is condemn'd already.</hi> To differ from an Orthodox Church, of which we are Members, tho in point of Ceremony, is very ſinful, if the difference is carry'd ſo far as to make a Schiſm: Toleration, tho' it ſecures us from the Laws of Men, not acquitting us at all in the ſight of God. But how much deeper is that Guilt, which lays the Ax to the Root of the Tree; and having corrupted our Minds, <hi>makes us reprobate concerning the Faith?</hi> An Enormity which the beſt and earlieſt Ages ſhew'd their deteſtation of by their frequent <hi>Anathema's</hi> againſt it.</p>
            <p>But of the ſecond, it does not ſeem ſo eaſie to pronounce. For if Men in the Fundamental Articles of our Holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion keep really, and unfeignedly to the truth of what is propos'd, as in the Trinity and Incarnation; ſhall we quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with them for uſing ſuch Words as are either unknown to Antiquity, or rejected by the Doctors of the preſent Church? May not God reveal to us what the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> or <hi>Chalcedon</hi> were ignorant of? And as long as we own the Subſtance of the Article as ſtrictly as our ſtricteſt Oppoſers, can any Fault be found with any Explication? Yet this will prove a wretched piece of Sophiſtry, if the following Inconveniencies are ſeriouſly conſider'd: 1<hi>ſt. That to depart from the Form which the Church has us'd herſelf to, is againſt her <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace.</hi> 2dly, <hi>That it is the way to unſettle pious Minds.</hi> 3dly, <hi>That it can never be done without giving the Adverſaries a mighty Advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:193432:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, It is againſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace of the Church.</hi> Words are the Interpreters of our Thoughts, and the only way we have to know one anothers Minds: A Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication which Nature has taught, Experience improv'd, and the mutual Commerce of Mankind rais'd to an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity. But if this is true in relation to the Affairs of this World, and is the Foundation of all Arts and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; how much more will it hold in reſpect to Religious Matters, where every Error is dangerous, and draws along with it ſo many fatal Conſequences? Religion, the grand Duty of Man, is convey'd into the Soul by hearing, and comes ſhort of its Energy, if the Terms which it is expreſt by, are unuſual, and do not in a great meaſure anſwer both its Nature, and the end which it propoſes. And Chriſtianity being to be diſſeminated, and the Goſpel to ſound to the Ends of the World; a Happineſs to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to the Jew and Gentile, to the <hi>Groecian</hi> and <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> to all Nations, Ages, Sexes, and Capacities, it was highly wiſe to deliver it in as ſhort a compaſs, and in as ſettled a manner of Expreſſion as the Nature of the thing could bear, and the difference of Men's Underſtandings agree with.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles having left us the Form of ſound Words, it became the Care of the Biſhops their Succeſſors to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it entire. But they ſaw an utter Impoſſibility of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and a door open to all manner of Schiſms, if Men were not confin'd to ſuch and ſuch Words, as well as ſuch and ſuch a ſence: And I dare preſume to ſay, that this ſunk ſo deeply into theſe holy and learned Men's Minds, that what we call in this Age Heats and Animoſities, or the <hi>Platonick</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotelian</hi> Philoſophy brought into the Church, was nothing elſe but an indefatigable Care and Induſtry to declare the Faith after ſuch a manner, as ſhould in after-Ages be kept inviolate.</p>
            <p>So afraid were the Fathers of new Words, new Lights,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:193432:12"/> new Expreſſions, new Explications, as that which naturally brings in a new Sence, that they ever look'd on them with a kind of Jealouſie; and would never admit them, till they were clearly underſtood, and authoriz'd by the common Conſent of the Chriſtian World. There is an eminent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this in the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which tho' the moſt expreſſive Words that could be, the one in relation to the Unity of the Divine Nature, the other in relation to the Subſiſtencies of the Divine Perſons; yet met with a vaſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, the one in the Greek, the other in the Latin Church, till a long canvaſſing, and at laſt the determination of the Sacred Councils had fix'd both their Uſe and their Sence.</p>
            <p>Innovation brings in Hereſie, and Hereſie ſhelters Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. The Apoſtle concludes the firſt to <hi>Timothy,</hi> by charging him pathetically <hi>to keep that which is committed to his Truſt, and to avoid profane and vain Babblings,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, vain and empty Sounds. The Latin Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reads more agreeably to the old Copies, <hi>profanas vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum novitates.</hi> I ſay more agreeably to the ancient Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies: For St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> read not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, new Sounds, new Words; which ſhews that it was ſo in the Exemplaries us'd by thoſe Fathers: Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which by being new are both ſuſpicious and dangerous.</p>
            <p>The Fathers of the third Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which is the ſixth General, and in which Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> and the <hi>Monothelites</hi> were condemn'd, were ſo ſenſible of the Evils occaſion'd by this, that they concluded their laſt Action, by ſubjecting to deprivation, if they were Biſhops or Clerks; or to Excommunication, if they were Laicks, whoſoever did bring in any <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, new Words, and new Explications: It being the Infirmity of Humane Nature to be ſtrangely affected with Novelty; and an Argument ſeldom wanting them, who take the glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering for the ſolid and weighty part of it. But when an Innovator, who has catch'd a bright Cloud inſtead of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:193432:13"/> Sun, comes to be encounter'd by the Orthodox, whoſe Zeal is ſo much the warmer, becauſe it is inflam'd by the Sence of an old Truth, then what Devaſtations, what Tragedies, what Schiſms, what Contentions are ſeen in the Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, It unſettles pious Minds.</hi> New Explications are like <hi>Meteors,</hi> which ſet Men on gazing, and always por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Ruine to Religion. When by an humble and ſettled Reverence for what God has propos'd to us by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of his Church, we have us'd our ſelves to a Form of Doctrine; whatſoever is foreign to it, offers our Minds an incredible Violence; Pious Ears are offended at it; and they who know better how to feel the Power of Religion, than to talk of it, are horribly ſcandaliz'd. They have us'd themſelves to an awful Belief and Adoration of Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. They have acquieſc'd in the receiv'd Expreſſions of the Univerſal Church; more ſecure in their reſt on the Breaſts of their Mother, than if all the Guards in the World were plac'd round about them; and conſequently ſtrangely aſtoniſh'd, when an Innovator ſtrives to tear them out of their Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>No Anſwer can be made to this, but a pretence of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that the <hi>Socinians</hi> have made it unavoidable in their Diſputes againſt the bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarnation,</hi> to run on a new Method; and that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> has taught us, and before him St. <hi>Cyprian;</hi> and of their Words a Canon has been made, That <hi>Melius eſt ut ſcandalum oriatur quam Veritas relinquatur. It is more tolerable to give an occaſion of ſcandal, than that Truth ſhould be left undefended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But where does the Neceſſity appear? Are we not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that the Arguments againſt our Myſteries are neither new nor invincible? Were not the <hi>Arrians</hi> much better Diſputants than the Scholars of <hi>Socinus,</hi> who are forc'd to give <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> the Face of <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> or elſe it is unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to the utmoſt degree. Has the old way of anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:193432:13"/> been yet worſted? Have not the deciſions of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils been like a Rock, on which indeed theſe proud Waves have beat; but have been forc'd back, broken, and diſpers'd? I humbly beg leave to ask, whether the receiv'd way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating theſe ſacred Doctrines can ſupport it ſelf or no? If it can; where is the neceſſity of any new one? And if it cannot; how comes that to be now ſo unſucceſsful, which the Church has been victorious by in all Ages and Places of the Chriſtian World?</p>
            <p>It fills learned Men with Grief and Indignation to ſee ſome of our late Authors ſtrive to entangle an Elephant in a Spider's Web, and expect the lamentable Iſſue of their Proceeding, who, as <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great expreſſes it, <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>mor. c.</hi> 17. <hi>Wanting Humility to be Diſciples of the Truth, become at laſt the Patrons of Error.</hi> The Eccleſiaſtical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory obſerves that the Great <hi>Baſil</hi> of <hi>Seleucia,</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nazianzum,</hi> before they offer'd to exerciſe their Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Function, did give themſelves for thirteen years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Retirement of a private Life, to the Study of the Holy Scriptures. <hi>Illarum ſententiam non ex proprio in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genio, ſed ex majorum ratione &amp; authoritate interpretantes.</hi> Not interpreting them as they pleas'd, ſays the Hiſtorian, but conforming their Interpretations to the Sence and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Ancients. A ſafe and an excellent Rule to us; and a noble Proof, by the way, of the Sence of the <hi>Ante-nicene</hi> Fathers: Theſe two eminent Biſhops having been ſo zealous of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith, which they had learn'd from the Reaſons and Authority of the Ancients in their Interpretations of Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, It cannot be done without giving the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries a mighty Advantage.</hi> By Adverſaries I mean all the Oppoſers of the ſacred Truths: But moſt particularly the <hi>Socinians;</hi> of whom it muſt be acknowledged, that in their firſt Prints they manag'd this Controverſie in a dull and languiſhing ſort of a way; and were really at a loſs, till
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:193432:14"/> the unwary manner of writing of ſome amongſt us, ſet them again on a full Cry, and made them more eager and vehement. Till then, their Objections were ſtale, and their Anſwers to ours ſtrain'd and unnatural. But ſome muſt pretend to explain things inexplicable, and underſtand things incomprehenſible. The <hi>Socinians</hi> ſenſible of the Advantage, remove all their Batteries, and place them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that weak ſide; and what work they were like to have made, if more accurate Writers had not ſtept in, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men ſee and grieve. Only diſingenuous in this, that when they have expos'd a Writer, they think to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the Church; as if the Church did warrant all their Inadvertencies, who pretend to write in her Defence; or eſpouſe private Notions, which ſhe never knew, nor ever will own.</p>
            <p>This eminently appears in one of their lateſt Prints, call'd <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the Real and Nominal Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> This they take to be the lucky hit. If you believe them, the Church is made up either of <hi>Tritheiſts,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally aſſert three Gods; or of <hi>Sabellians,</hi> who mean no more by three Perſons, than three meer Modes or Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and this Notion they have carry'd ſo far, and ſo throughly perſwaded themſelves of the Truth and Strength of it, that it has ſwallow'd up all their other Topicks. Whereas there never was perhaps a more unjuſt way of arguing in the World: For the Church is ſo far from being divided into ſuch Real and Nominal Trinitarians, as they are pleas'd to repreſent us, that there is no ſuch thing in Nature. There is no Church, or part of the Church, which believes any more than one Infinite and Eternal God. There is no Church, or part of the Church, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver plac'd the Trinity of Perſons in meer Modes, Relations, Names, or Offices. There is no Church, or part of the Church, but what has admitted a Real Unity in Trinity, and a Real Trinity in Unity, but has declar'd the <hi>Modus,</hi> or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to be altogether incomprehenſible.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:193432:14"/>
            <p>But where then have the <hi>Socinians</hi> met with a ground for this bold Aſſertion? Truly from ſome unhappy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Men, who have not been judicious and exact e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſee all the Conſequences which flow from their Principles; and have not perceiv'd that an Adverſary could not be oblig'd to be ſo equitable, as not to carry thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences further than ever they were intended. The <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> did hear ſome talk of Three Infinite Minds and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; an Expreſſion indeed harſh and new! And an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Mind, or Spirit, being the definition of God, they have concluded that they aſſerted Three Gods. But they have not had the Juſtice to conſider, that they who aſſerted Three Infinite Minds and Spirits, aſſerted them in one altogether indiviſible and inſeparable, that is, in a Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical Nature. On the other ſide, they have heard that the Three Perſons were the ſeveral Modes, and Relations of the Divine Nature. They preſently run upon the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Modes in created Beings, which are only the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Affections of Subſtances; and concluded that ſuch a ſort of a Trinity is only of Modes and Denominations: But they have not had the Juſtice to conſider that the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Modes of Subſiſtence,</hi> are quite of another Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; That whatſoever is in God, is God; That the Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtences and Relations are all ſubſtantial; and that the Church never pretended, nor theſe Authors themſelves, that they could give any adequate repreſentation of an Object incomprehenſible.</p>
            <p>In the mean time they have made a diverſion; heated ſeveral great and learned Men one againſt another; and by equally miſrepreſenting both, have given us a ſad Inſtance how dangerous it is to depart from the Form of ſound Words.</p>
            <p>I draw now to a Concluſion; and come to ſhew, how we ought to behave our ſelves in relation to them who have departed from it. Our behaviour muſt be limited by ſo many ſeveral Rules, as there are Perſons who have done it.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:193432:15"/> Firſt, Thoſe without, who have departed from the Article it ſelf. Secondly, Thoſe within, who have departed from the Terms which the Church expreſſes it by.</p>
            <p>The only Adverſaries of the Sacred Doctrine in this Age, are the <hi>Socinians.</hi> I humbly conceive, that that part of the Injunctions which concerns the Angels of the Church, the moſt Reverend the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, is no part of our buſineſs: We muſt not preſume to preſcribe to them from whom we ought to receive Laws: They are the Principle of Order and Unity in the Church: They are Stars of the firſt Magnitude, and in that Elevation of Zeal and Knowledge, that as they ſee farther, and move in a far larger extent than we do; ſo they cannot be wanting to themſelves, when grievous Wolves enter in amongſt us, not ſparing the Flock. I confine my ſelf to us, who, by the Truſt committed to our Care, may come to be engag'd in theſe Diſputes.</p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> ſeveral are Perſons of Learning and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, acquainted with all the fine ſort of Literature, and who have done for and in a bad Cauſe as much as Men can do: It is an Honour to the Church to have ſuch Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to deal with. Truth never appears with more force, than when it is moſt ſtrongly oppos'd. In our late Diſputes againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> a ſmall Stock of Learning and Common Sence was enough to ſhew its Folly. In the wrangling War with the Diſſenters, we have been forc'd to argue with a ſort of Writers who ſcarce underſtood good Language. But in this, we meet with a ſubtil and ſtrong Enemy, well fitted with all Materials for War; and I look upon it as a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, who turns all things to the good of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that this Controverſie will put us of the Clergy upon finer, better, and more comprehenſive Studies.</p>
            <p>But there is another ſort of <hi>Socinians;</hi> and they are they who pretend to make a Buſtle in the World; Men, who, after a long courſe of Atheiſm and Debauchery, come at
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:193432:15"/> laſt to think of Religion; not becauſe they deſign to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the ends, or ſubmit to the Duties of it, but becauſe in an Age where ſo many Religions are allow'd, it is not hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to be without one. They live ſtill as they did before, with as little care as ever of their Eternal Concerns; but think Religion only to conſiſt in talking at randon of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Matters. Theſe Heroes ſcorn to fall upon ſome part of the Diſcipline and Liturgy of the Church, as other Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals have done, but preſently impeach its Faith, its Articles; ſtare Mankind in the face; and with that mouth us'd before to blaſpheme and reproach their Maker, they dare to deny the Lord that bought them. Every Club, Coffee-houſe, or Tavern, is the Scene of the Tragedy; and Religion, the moſt ſerious and grave buſineſs of Man's Life, the Exerciſe of the Church, Family, or Cloſer, is villainouſly proſtituted over a Diſh of Coffee, or a Bottle of Wine.</p>
            <p>The way to deal with theſe, is not to diſpute: An evil heart of Unbelief has turn'd them aſide, that they cannot ſay there is a Lye in my right hand: They are to be the Object of our Prayers, and Tears to God for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. The laſt Argument that remains, is by our good Examples to bring them to ſome Sence of Morality.</p>
            <p>But againſt the others, we ought to diſpute and to write: When Error is always ready to ſpeak, Truth ought not to be ſilent. We cannot be afraid of a Cauſe, which the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Company of the Apoſtles has taught, the Noble Army of Martyrs maintain'd, and the Holy Church throughout all the World ſo ſolemnly acknowledg'd. But it is diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be obſerv'd, that few Reaſons, and theſe good; Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and theſe not conteſted; an exact and accurate way of writing, are the means to ſtop a Controverſie. Above all things, Heat and Paſſion ought to claim no part in the Diſpute: Ill Language is a bad Introduction for the beſt Argument. Either we deſign to confute, inſtruct, and perſwade them, or we do not: If we do not, we detain
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:193432:16"/> the Truth of God in Hypocriſie, and make it ſubſervient to mean and inglorious Ends: And if we do, we cannot but be ſenſible, that Truth, Gravity, Exactneſs, and Strength of Reaſon, are ſtrangely obſtructed by a ſordid and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious way of writing.</p>
            <p>But if we are to be ſo juſt to them without, how much more to them within? It is one of the Exceſſes which God reproaches the Wicked with, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 50.20. <hi>to ſit and ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Brother, to ſlander his own Mother's Son.</hi> A Sin not allowable in the Jewiſh, much leſs in the Chriſtian Church; not pardonable in a Laick, much leſs in a Clerk. It has been obſerv'd of the old <hi>Romans,</hi> that they ſcarce ever felt any Convulſion in their State, till their victorious Arms were turn'd againſt themſelves, and deſtroy'd in very few years the Proſperity of many Ages. It has appear'd all along, our Adverſaries themſelves being Judges, that the great Piety, mighty Genius, vaſt Parts, profound Learning, and flowing Eloquence of the Clergy of this Nation, has made the Church of <hi>England</hi> venerable to all the World: They have brought the Clamouring Papiſt to ſhame and deſpair of Succeſs: They have ſilenc'd the buzzing Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt. No Argument has fallen into their hands, but what they have exhauſted with an incredible Felicity of Thought and Expreſſion; and muſt we turn thoſe never foil'd Weapons into our own Bowels? Is this a time to become the Contrivers of our own ruine, whilſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my takes breath, and has nothing left to do, but to inflame our unhappy Contentions?</p>
            <p>I am not for ſtifling the Truth. God forbid! It would be in vain; for it is great, and it muſt prevail. I would have Zeal to take its courſe, and our mouth to be open, and our heart enlarg'd to all Men: But at the ſame time I would have fervent Charity amongſt our ſelves; and think it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable to bite and devour one another, till we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd of one another.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:193432:16"/>
            <p>To avoid ſo dangerous an Exceſs, let us take leave of our Paſſions when we begin to ſpeak or write about theſe Sacred Matters. Paſſion hinders us from taking the real Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of an Argument, and makes us to adminiſter Poiſon inſtead of a Medicine. It generally puts us on the wrong ſide of the Queſtion; and the <hi rend="blackletterType">Man</hi> does ſadly expoſe the Writer. It has the ſame Effect on him againſt whom we write: It hurries him to a retaliation; and between two hot Spirits, Truth vaniſhes, and only the wrangling part remains. It is that which we abhor in Converſation, and is not ſuffer'd amongſt civiliz'd People. We wrangle in Print, and ſtamp on Paper the laſting marks of Fury and Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. In the mean time the Judicious Reader pities Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Weakneſs; wants a ſtock of Patience to read the Book through, and leaves us at laſt to the Judgment of the great Judge. But a judicious Reader is ſomewhat rare. The looſe witty People ſwallow greedily the ſarcaſtical, and leave the ſerious part. By this Religion is expos'd, and cruelly miſrepreſented. This has been the ground of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Canons taken from the grave Admonitions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and in particular the 53 of our Church.</p>
            <p>Let us unanimouſly return to the Form of found Words. That which ſhews the Vanity and Unpracticableneſs of Explications beyond the Power of Contradiction, is, that there is none but what is liable to invincible Objections; and indeed how can it be otherwiſe, when the Subject tranſcends all our Apprehenſions? Man who is ſcarce ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with himſelf, will pretend to decide of the Nature of God! A poor, finite, and limited Being, will become a Judge of Eternity, and Immenſity! One who does not know the leaſt of his Soul's Operations, will preſume to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſeveral ways of Communication of the Divine Nature! <hi rend="blackletterType">Away</hi> with this pretended Knowledge, which at the bottom is nothing but Noiſe and Talk! <hi rend="blackletterType">Away</hi> with that glittering Nonſence, which is not worthy to take up
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:193432:17"/> a ſerious Man's leiſure! For my part I am reſolv'd to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore, and to Believe. I will give an unfeigned Aſſent to what is reveal'd; and come to God with the Homage and Submiſſion of my Underſtanding, concerning what he is pleas'd to conceal from me. I will have mean Thoughts of this preſent Life, ſince in it we know ſo little; and a mighty deſire of that which is to come, ſince in it we ſhall know ſo much. In the mean time, I ſhall conclude this Diſcourſe with the excellent Prayer of St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> in his 12th. Book of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and doubt not, my <hi rend="blackletterType">Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Brethren,</hi> but you will join with me in it. <hi>Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va hanc Conſcientiae meae vocem, ut quod in regenerationis meae ſymbolo baptizatus in Patre, Filio, &amp; Spiritu Sancto profeſſus ſum, ſemper obtineam. Preſerve in me, O Lord, that Anſwer of a good Conſcience, that I may ever hold faſt what I have profeſs'd at my Regeneration, when I was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To theſe Three Co-eternal, Co-eſſential, Conſubstantial Perſons, in that one Adorable, Indiviſible, and Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the Father Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the only Begotten Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, God of God, Light of Light, very God of very God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the Holy and Eternal Spirit proceeding from the Father and the Son,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All Honour and Glory now and for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:193432:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
